<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Astrophysics for Babies</title>
  
  
  <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/"/>
  <updated>2024-05-18T05:28:43.458Z</updated>
  <id>https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Ryan Guo</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ryan Guo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/32545.html"/>
    <id>https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/32545.html</id>
    <published>2024-05-18T05:06:18.955Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-18T05:28:43.458Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class="math display">\[\begin{align}\nabla\cdot\boldsymbol{D}&amp;=\rho_0\nonumber \\\nabla\times\boldsymbol{E}&amp;=-\frac{\partial\boldsymbol{B}}{\partialt}\nonumber \\ \nabla\cdot\boldsymbol{B}&amp;=0\nonumber \\\nabla\times\boldsymbol{H}&amp;=\boldsymbol{j}_0+\frac{\partial\boldsymbol{D}}{\partial t}\nonumber \end{align}\]</span></p><p>Welcome to my homepage!</p><p>This is a dumb undergraduate majoring in physics in an unknownuniversity. I've studied some astronomy myself but haven't figured outanything T_T</p><p>But I really want to study astrophysics aaaaaaaaaaaaaaaa</p><p>I may post some study materials and daily thoughts here.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;&#92;[&#92;begin{align}
&#92;nabla&#92;cdot&#92;boldsymbol{D}&amp;amp;=&#92;rho_0&#92;nonumber &#92;&#92;
&#92;nabla&#92;times&#92;boldsymbol{E}&amp;amp;=-&#92;frac{&#92;pa</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Too Many Crazy Teachers🥵</title>
    <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/20082.html"/>
    <id>https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/20082.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-12T08:26:27.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-18T12:25:20.727Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first year I didn't feel anything, but the second year I realizedthat there were too many mad teachers at the university.🥵🥵🥵</p><p>This semester there are three courses: Optics, Theoretical Mechanicsand Mathematical Methods for Physics. The only one that's normal is MMP(after all, it's the God of MMP, Guoquan Zhou). But the teachers of theremaining two classes are a bit crazy.</p><h2 id="theoretical-mechanics">Theoretical Mechanics</h2><p>The textbook is Landau, which is not suitable for beginners. Thisbook is not suitable as a textbook for beginners, it has no mathematicaldetails and the notation is different from other books. In the end, Ichose to follow along with other books.</p><p>And I'm a sophomore, sophomore, sophomore, and I haven't finished themath and physics stuff yet, and even though you're in astrophysics andI'm interested in it, all of a sudden there's a lot of metrics andgeneral relativity and abstract metrics and tensor analysis and it justmakes me feel like I'm taking a very abstract class.</p><p>Conclusion: self-study.</p><h2 id="optics">Optics</h2><span id="more"></span><p>I don't have a problem with the teacher's lectures, but can byd go inorder of difficulty and generalization. The first lesson first byd talkMaxwell's system of equations how to derive the electromagnetic waveequation, where I learned vector analysis uh uh uh, have to talk aboutthe introduction to electrodynamics is it. Then the second class is aquick lesson in geometric optics, not even polarization, just interfacereflection and refraction Fresnel formula, I byd 8 am already sleepy andstill have to give me a sleep aid, right?</p><p>Conclusion: self-study.</p><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>College is about developing your self-learning skills, and so are therequired courses.🤣👉</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first year I didn&#39;t feel anything, but the second year I realized
that there were too many mad teachers at the university.🥵🥵🥵&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This semester there are three courses: Optics, Theoretical Mechanics
and Mathematical Methods for Physics. The only one that&#39;s normal is MMP
(after all, it&#39;s the God of MMP, Guoquan Zhou). But the teachers of the
remaining two classes are a bit crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;theoretical-mechanics&quot;&gt;Theoretical Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The textbook is Landau, which is not suitable for beginners. This
book is not suitable as a textbook for beginners, it has no mathematical
details and the notation is different from other books. In the end, I
chose to follow along with other books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&#39;m a sophomore, sophomore, sophomore, and I haven&#39;t finished the
math and physics stuff yet, and even though you&#39;re in astrophysics and
I&#39;m interested in it, all of a sudden there&#39;s a lot of metrics and
general relativity and abstract metrics and tensor analysis and it just
makes me feel like I&#39;m taking a very abstract class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: self-study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;optics&quot;&gt;Optics&lt;/h2&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Various" scheme="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/categories/Various/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Initial Understanding of the Concept of Metrics</title>
    <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/24556.html"/>
    <id>https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/24556.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-07T06:12:17.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-18T12:26:08.408Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I read the new book "Classical Mechanics" by Prof.Xian Gao from Sun Yat-sen University, and I have a preliminaryunderstanding of the concept of "metric".</p><p>The key lies in the fact that Prof. Gao combines some of our existingconcepts with some advanced mathematical tools, and introduces newconcepts in a more concise and easy-to-understand language.</p><h2 id="generalization-of-the-pythagorean-theorem">Generalization of thePythagorean Theorem</h2><p>We know that in flat Euclidian space, the distance between two pointscan be expressed by the Pythagorean theorem: <spanclass="math display">\[\begin{equation}\label{eq1}\mathrm{d}s^2=\mathrm{d}x^2+\mathrm{d}y^2,\end{equation}\]</span> or in polar coordinates: <span class="math display">\[\begin{equation}\label{eq2}\mathrm{d}s^2=\mathrm{d}\rho^2+\rho^2\mathrm{d}\varphi^2.\end{equation}\]</span> <span id="more"></span></p><p>So in other spaces, the Pythagorean theorem still holds as long asone takes <strong>infinitely small distances</strong> so that the spaceis approximately flat and linear. For example, on a sphere: <spanclass="math display">\[\begin{equation}\label{eq3}\mathrm{d}s^2=R^2\mathrm{d}\theta^2+R^2\sin^2\theta\,\mathrm{d}\varphi^2.\end{equation}\]</span></p><h2 id="write-the-pythagorean-theorem-in-quadratic-form">Write thePythagorean theorem in quadratic form</h2><p>Although the Pythagorean theorem holds in different spaces andcoordinate systems, their forms seem to be less uniform (e.g. <spanclass="math inline">\(\eqref{eq1}\)</span>, <spanclass="math inline">\(\eqref{eq2}\)</span> and <spanclass="math inline">\(\eqref{eq3}\)</span>). But each of them is asquare term. This prompted us to think of the quadratic forms we learnedin linear algebra. So we try to write the above three Pythagoreantheorems in the form of quadratic matrices: <spanclass="math inline">\(\eqref{eq3}\)</span> and <spanclass="math inline">\(\eqref{eq3}\)</span>. <spanclass="math display">\[\begin{align}\mathrm{d}s^2&amp;=\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}x&amp;\mathrm{d}y\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}1&amp;0\\0&amp;1\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}x\\\mathrm{d}y\end{pmatrix},\\[12pt]\mathrm{d}s^2&amp;=\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\rho&amp;\mathrm{d}\varphi\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}1&amp;0\\0&amp;\rho^2\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\rho\\\mathrm{d}\varphi\end{pmatrix},\\[12pt]\mathrm{d}s^2&amp;=\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\theta&amp;\mathrm{d}\varphi\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}R^2&amp;0\\0&amp;R^2\sin^2\theta\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\theta\\\mathrm{d}\varphi\end{pmatrix}.\end{align}\]</span> It turns out that <span class="math display">\[\begin{equation}\mathrm{d}s^2\equiv\mathrm{d}\boldsymbol{\rho}^\mathrm{T}\,G\,\mathrm{d}\boldsymbol{\rho}.\end{equation}\]</span> Uniform in form, now that's a good thing. We can write ageneralized form <span class="math display">\[\begin{equation}\mathrm{d}s^2=\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\rho^1&amp;\cdots&amp;\mathrm{d}\rho^s\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}g_{11}&amp;\cdots&amp;g_{1s}\\\vdots&amp;\ddots&amp;\vdots\\g_{s1}&amp;\cdots&amp;g_{ss}\end{pmatrix}\begin{pmatrix}\mathrm{d}\rho^1\\\vdots\\\mathrm{d}q^s\end{pmatrix}.\end{equation}\]</span> So we define the matrix <spanclass="math inline">\(g_{ab}\)</span> as a <strong>metric</strong>. Sothe above three examples and other spatial/targeting metrics are clear:P.</p><p>So to summarize, the <strong>metric is a generalization of thePythagorean theorem to infinitesimal distances</strong>.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I read the new book &quot;Classical Mechanics&quot; by Prof.
Xian Gao from Sun Yat-sen University, and I have a preliminary
understanding of the concept of &quot;metric&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key lies in the fact that Prof. Gao combines some of our existing
concepts with some advanced mathematical tools, and introduces new
concepts in a more concise and easy-to-understand language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;generalization-of-the-pythagorean-theorem&quot;&gt;Generalization of the
Pythagorean Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that in flat Euclidian space, the distance between two points
can be expressed by the Pythagorean theorem: &lt;span
class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;&#92;[
&#92;begin{equation}
&#92;label{eq1}
&#92;mathrm{d}s^2=&#92;mathrm{d}x^2+&#92;mathrm{d}y^2,
&#92;end{equation}
&#92;]&lt;/span&gt; or in polar coordinates: &lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;&#92;[
&#92;begin{equation}
&#92;label{eq2}
&#92;mathrm{d}s^2=&#92;mathrm{d}&#92;rho^2+&#92;rho^2&#92;mathrm{d}&#92;varphi^2.
&#92;end{equation}
&#92;]&lt;/span&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Various" scheme="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/categories/Various/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Previous Problems of the Final Round of the Chinese National Astronomy Olympiad (CNAO) (2002-2022)</title>
    <link href="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/56951.html"/>
    <id>https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/posts/56951.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-07T05:30:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-18T12:27:15.762Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a newbie(T_T) who has only participated once in CNAO, I'veorganized some test questions from previous years in my free time beforeand after the olympiad. I'm going to put them up for future BR'sreference (orz).</p><p><a href="/download/papers/cnao_final_2002-2020.pdf">Final roundproblems of Chinese National Astronomy Olympiad(2002-2020)</a></p><p><a href="/download/papers/cnao_final_2022.pdf">Final round problemsof Chinese National Astronomy Olympiad (2021-2022)</a></p><p><a href="/download/papers/cnao_final_2022_video.mp4">Video forProblem 3 in CNAO 2021-2022</a></p><p>It's not easy to organize, try not to spread it widely, but you canpromote this site when you share it QAQ (</p><p>If there are any omissions or updates, please feel free to contactme.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a newbie(T_T) who has only participated once in CNAO, I&#39;ve
organized some test questions from previous years in my free time before
</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="Problems" scheme="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/categories/Problems/"/>
    
    <category term="CNAO" scheme="https://ryan-gwo.github.io/en/categories/Problems/CNAO/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
